# **Mahsan Nourani**

Human-centered AI/XAI . Responsible AI . Decision-making . Visual Analytics

My interdisciplinary research lies in the intersection of HCl, Al/ML, psychology, and social sciences. I study people's interactions with and understanding of Al/ML systems, specifically those used for Al-assisted decision-making. My research has implications for building ethical and responsible Al systems.

<u>★ www.mahsan.page</u>

in LinkedIn

<u> mahsannourani@ufl.edu</u>

Github

Google Scholar

Research Experience

Aug 2018 - Present University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida

Research Assistant Advisor: <u>Eric D. Ragan</u>

May 2022 – Aug 2022 Apple Inc., Sunnyvale, California

Research Intern, Technology Development Group

Mentor: Marco Cavallo

May 2021 – Aug 2021 Microsoft Research, New York, New York

Research Intern, Fairness, Accountability, Transparency, & Ethics (FATE) team Mentor: Hal Daumé III, Jenn Wortman Vaughan, Solon Barocas, Forough Poursabzi

Aug 2017 – Aug 2018 Texas A&M University, College Station, Texas

Research Assistant Advisor: <u>Eric D. Ragan</u>

Feb 2015 – Jun 2017 University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advisor: Hadi Moradi

**Education** 

Aug 2017 - May 2023 Ph.D., Computer Science

University of Florida (Transferred: Texas A&M University in 2018), Gainesville, Florida

Thesis: "Shadows of the Past: The Effects of User's Past Experiences and Expectations on Human-Al

Partnership"

Advisor: Eric D. Ragan

Committee: Juan Gilbert, Jenn Wortman Vaughan, Peter Kvam, Vincent Binschaedler

Dec 2021 M.S., Computer Science

University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida

GPA: 3.80/4.0

Sep 2012 – Jun 2017 B.E., Information Technology (Computer Engineering)

University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

Thesis: "Teaching Turn-taking to Children with Autism"

GPA: 3.70/4.0

**Honors and Awards** 

2022 Doctoral Colloquium Fellowship

IEEE Visualization & Visual Analytics Conference, Participant & Recipient

2021 ACM IUI Best Paper Award (C.5)

Honorable Mention, Recipient

2021, 2022 Gartner Group Graduate Fellowship

Herbert Wertheim College of Engineering, University of Florida, Recipient

2021 - 2023 Special Recognition for Outstanding Review

ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Recipient

#### 2020 Outstanding Achievement Award (Top 9%)

Herbert Wertheim College of Engineering, University of Florida, Recipient

#### 2016 4th Iran Game Developers Cup (team participation)

Kashan, Iran, Winner

#### 2012 Nationwide University Entrance Exam in Mathematics and Physics (Top 0.1%)

Tehran, Iran, Ranked 542th

## 2012 Nationwide University Entrance Exam in English and Foreign Languages (Top 0.4%)

Tehran, Iran, Ranked 242th

#### **Publications**

#### **Refereed Journal Papers**

#### J.4 DETOXER: A Visual Debugging Tool with Multi-Scope Explanations for Temporal Multi-Label Classification

Mahsan Nourani, Chiradeep Roy, Donald Honeycutt, Eric Ragan, Vibhav Gogate

IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications (CG&A). (To appear) (2022)

#### J.3 On the Importance of User Backgrounds and Impressions: Lessons Learned from Interactive AI Applications

Mahsan Nourani, Chiradeep Roy, Jeremy Block, Donald Honeycutt, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Vibhav Gogate ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (TiiS). (2022)

J.2 Explainable Activity Recognition in Videos: Lessons Learned

Chiradeep Roy, **Mahsan Nourani**, Jeremy Block, Donald Honeycutt, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Nicholas Ruozzi, Vibhav Gogate Applied Al Letters. (2021)

J.1 SplitStreams: A Visual Metaphor for Evolving Hierarchies

Fabian Bolte, Mahsan Nourani, Eric Ragan, Stefen Bruckner

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG). (2020)

#### **Refereed Conference Papers**

#### 🙎 C.5 Anchoring Bias Affects Mental Model Formation and User Reliance in Explainable AI Systems

**Mahsan Nourani**, Chiradeep Roy, Jeremy Block, Donald Honeycutt, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Vibhav Gogate

26th International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI). (2021)

Test paper, Honorable Mention Award

## C.4 Understanding the Effects of Explanation Types and User Motivations on Recommender System Use

Qing Li, Sharon Chu, Nanjie Rao, Mahsan Nourani

Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP). (2021)

# C.3 Soliciting Human-in-the-Loop User Feedback for Interactive Machine Learning Reduces User Trust and Impressions of Model Accuracy

Donald Honeycutt, Mahsan Nourani, Eric Ragan

Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP). (2021)

#### C.2 The Role of Domain Expertise in User Trust and The Impact of First Impressions with Intelligent Systems

Mahsan Nourani, Joanie King, Eric Ragan

Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP). (2020)

#### C.1 The Effects of Meaningful and Meaningless Explanations on Trust and Perceived System Accuracy in Intelligent Systems

Mahsan Nourani, Samia Kabir, Sina Mohseni, Eric Ragan

Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP). (2019)

#### **Conference Workshop Papers, Posters, and Presentations**

# P.5 Shadows of the Past: The Effects of User's Past Experiences and Expectations on Human-Al Partnership Mahsan Nourani

IEEE Visualization and Visual Analytics Conference, Doctoral Colloquium (DC). (2022)

## P.4 Romadoro: Leveraging Nudge Techniques to Encourage Break-Taking

Katarina Jurczyk, Christopher You, **Mahsan Nourani**, Manas Gupta, Lisa Anthony, Benjamin Lok The ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST). **(2021)** 

## P3 Investigating the Importance of First Impressions and Explainable AI with Interactive Video Analysis

**Mahsan Nourani**, Chiradeep Roy, Donald Honeycutt, Jeremy Block, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Vibhav Gogate Extended Abstracts of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI LBW). (2020)

P.2 Explainable Activity Recognition in Videos

Chiradeep Roy, Mahesh Shanbhag, **Mahsan Nourani**, Tahrima Rahman, Samia Kabir, Vibhav Gogate, Nicholas Ruozzi, Eric Ragan IUI 2nd workshop on Explainable Smart Systems (ExSS, now TEXSS). (2019)

#### P.1 Explainable Activity Recognition in Videos using Dynamic Cutset Networks

Chiradeep Roy, **Mahsan Nourani**, Mahesh Shanbhag, Samia Kabir, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Nicholas Ruozzi, Vibhav Gogate 3rd Workshop of Tractable Probabilistic Modeling (TPM 2019). **(2019)** 

#### **Pre-prints**

A.1 Don't Explain without Verifying Veracity: An Evaluation of Explainable AI with Video Activity Recognition

**Mahsan Nourani**, Chiradeep Roy, Tahrima Rahman, Eric Ragan, Nicholas Ruozzi, Vibhav Gogate arXiv:2005.02335 (2020)

#### Talks and Presentations

#### Shadows of the Past: The Effects of User's Past Experiences and Expectations on Human-AI Partnership

- 2022 IEEE Visualization & Visual Analytics Conference, Doctoral Colloquium 😩 Invited Talk
- 2022 University of Florida Thesis Proposal

## Beware of the Biases: The Role of User Biases in Explainable AI Systems

- 2021 Microsoft Research 
  ☐ Invited Talk
- 2021 Visualization Summer Camp 
  ☐ Invited Talk

#### The Effects of Predicting and Explaining People's Errors on Their Predictions

2021 Intern Tea Talk, Microsoft Research

## Anchoring Bias Affects Mental Model Formation and User Reliance in Explainable AI Systems

- 2021 ACM Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)
- 2021 DARPA eXplainable AI (XAI) Program Workshop
- 2020 University of Florida affiliated Virtual CHI

#### Splitstreams: A Visual Metaphor for Evolving Hierarchies

2020 IEEE Visualization & Visual Analytics Conference, Co-presented

## The Role of Domain Expertise in User Trust and The Impact of First Impressions with Intelligent Systems

2020 AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP)

#### The effects of Explanation Meaningfulness and Veracity on Intelligent System Usage

- 2019 The UFII Student Data Analysis Seminar (SDAS) 🖻 Invited Talk
- 2019 AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing (HCOMP)

## **Teaching Experience**

#### **Guest Lecturer: Human-Computer Interactions (CEN 4721)**

University of Florida - Spring 2021, Spring 2022

Lecture on introduction to Human-Centered AI and Explainable AI

#### Teaching Assistant: Introduction to Computer Systems and Programming (C)

University of Tehran - Fall 2015

Project Chief TA and Lab Coordinator. Supervised 10 TAs and over 220 students.

## Teaching Assistant: Advanced Programming (C++)

University of Tehran - Fall 2014, Spring 2015

HW desiner and held extra-curricular lectures.

## Teaching Assistant: Data Structures and Algorithms (Java)

University of Tehran - Spring 2015, Fall 2015

HW desiner and held extra-curricular lectures

#### **Grader: Probability and Statistics**

University of Tehran - Fall 2015

# **Mentoring Experience**

2019 – 2021 Donald Honeycutt, Ph.D. student at University of Florida

As the project lead, I taught him the ropes of doing research in the first 2 years of their PhD.

2019 - 2021 Jeremy Block, Ph.D. student at University of Florida

As the project lead, I taught him the ropes of doing research in the first 2 years of their PhD.

Summer 2019 Ezekiel Ajayi, BE. student at University of Maryland, Baltimore County

Mentor through the NSF's Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program.

## **Service Activities**

#### **Organizer**

University of Florida Affiliated Virtual CHI (conference cancelled due to COVID) -2020

#### **Program Committee**

<u>IEEE VIS Workshop on TRust and EXpertise in Visualization (TREX)</u> — 2022, 2021, 2020

ACM CHI workshop on Human-Centered Explainable AI (HCXAI) - 2022

NeurIPS workshop on Human-Centered AI (HCAI) - 2022

#### Reviewer

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG) - 2022, 2021

ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work And Social Computing (CSCW) - 2023

<u>IEEE Visualization and Visual Analytics Conference (VIS)</u> — 2022, 2021

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) - 2023, 2022, 2021

Workshop on Visualization for AI Explainability (VISxAI) - 2021

## **Volunteer Experience**

October 2021 Student Volunteer

IEEE Visualization & Visual Analytics Conference, Remote

2021, 2020, 2019 Student Volunteer

Prospective PhD stduent visit weekend, University of Florida

November 2019 Event Coordinator

CodeIT Day Event (CS programming workshop for underpriviledged K12 students), Belle Glade, Fl

Summer 2019 Graduate Mentor and Coordinator

NSF IMHCI-REU Program, University of Florida

2016 Journalist

ACM Student Chapter F1 Magazine, University of Tehran

2014 – 2017 Student Body & Member

University of Tehran Game Club Student Chapter, University of Tehran